<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd">

<issue num="4328" status="Tentatively Ready">
<title>Remove note in &sect;[exec.sched] regarding waiting for completion of scheduled operations</title>
<section>
<sref ref="[exec.sched]"/>
</section>
<submitter>Lewis Baker</submitter>
<date>25 Aug 2025</date>
<priority>99</priority>

<discussion>
<p>
The note at the end of <sref ref="[exec.sched]"/> says:
</p>
<blockquote><p>
[<i>Note</i>: The ability to wait for completion of submitted function objects can be provided by the 
associated execution resource of the scheduler &mdash; <i>end note</i>]
</p></blockquote>
<p>
The suggestion that the execution resource should be used to join/wait on scheduled work is problematic 
in situations that may involve more than one execution context, as an execution resource having an empty 
queue of scheduled work does not necessarily imply that tasks currently running on another execution 
context will not later schedule additional work on this execution resource.
<p/>
With the introduction of `counting_scope` with <paper num="P3149"/> we now have a better recommended 
way of waiting for tasks that use a resource (including execution resources) to complete.
<p/>
The note as it stands represents bad guidance and should either be removed or updated to refer to 
`counting_scope` and `simple_counting_scope` (<sref ref="[exec.counting.scopes]"/>).
</p>

<note>2025-10-23; Reflector poll.</note>
<p>
Set status to Tentatively Ready after six votes in favour during reflector poll.
</p>
<p>
"What is this telling me as a user? That a custom execution resource can add
a non-standard 'wait for completion' facility?"
</p>
</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>
This wording is relative to <paper num="N5014"/>.
</p>

<ol>

<li><p>Modify <sref ref="[exec.sched]"/> as indicated:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>
-7- A scheduler type's destructor shall not block pending completion of any receivers connected to the sender
objects returned from schedule.
<p/>
<del>[<i>Note 1</i>: The ability to wait for completion of submitted function objects can be provided by 
the associated execution resource of the scheduler. &mdash; <i>end note</i>]</del>
</p>
</blockquote>

</li>

</ol>
</resolution>

</issue>
